<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>

<!DOCTYPE xmlmanual SYSTEM "../wimp.dtd">

<!-- Copyright 2020-2026, Stephen Fryatt (info@stevefryatt.org.uk)
   -
   - This file is part of Wimp Programming In C:
   -
   -   http://www.stevefryatt.org.uk/risc-os/wimp-prog
   -
   - Licensed under the EUPL, Version 1.2 only (the "Licence");
   - You may not use this work except in compliance with the
   - Licence.
   -
   - You may obtain a copy of the Licence at:
   -
   -   http://joinup.ec.europa.eu/software/page/eupl
   -
   - Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in
   - writing, software distributed under the Licence is
   - distributed on an "AS IS" basis, WITHOUT WARRANTIES
   - OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   -
   - See the Licence for the specific language governing
   - permissions and limitations under the Licence.
  -->

<manual xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="xmldoc.xsd" version="1.8.6">

<!-- Chapter 31
   -
   - Window Redraw
  -->

<chapter id="chap-redraw">
<resources>
<images>Chapter31</images>
<downloads>Chapter31</downloads>
</resources>
<filename>window-redraw.php</filename>
<uri>window-redraw</uri>
<title>Window Redraw</title>

<summary>We can break free from the limitations of icons by drawing our own windows!</summary>

<section>
<p>So far in our investigations into the Wimp, we have managed to create all of our windows using just icons. For many purposes &ndash; especially standard dialogue boxes &ndash; this is fine: it&rsquo;s what icons are designed to do, and leaving the Wimp to handle all of the work of drawing the window contents on to the screen is a lot easier than trying to do it ourselves.</p>

<p>Depending on the type of applications that they work on, many developers may find that this approach is fine for the vast majority &ndash; if not all &ndash; of the applications that they create. However, there are many places where icons don&rsquo;t work well. An obvious example are windows in which documents or graphics are created, such as <cite>ArtWorks</cite> or <cite>Ovation&nbsp;Pro</cite> files, where a mixture of arbitrary text and graphics need to be displayed. A less obvious situation would be when displaying tabular data like a spreadsheet: icons <em>could</em> be used, but this quickly becomes slow and &ndash; as we saw before we <reference id="chap-templates">introduced window templates</reference> &ndash; keeping track of all of the indirected data that we need soon becomes a headache.</p>

<image id="fig-redraw-examples" file="redraw-examples.png" title="Three windows which use manual redraw"/>

<p>For many applications, including <cite>ArtWorks</cite> on the left of <reference id="fig-redraw-examples"/>, the best approach is to use a completely blank window and redraw <em>everything</em> that they need from first principles using <swi>OS_Plot</swi>, the Draw module and the Font manager. If the need is for something more &lsquo;icon-like&rsquo;, such as the table from <cite>CashBook</cite> on the bottom-right, then there is a middle ground available to us: we can handle the redraw ourselves, but use the Wimp&rsquo;s icon plotting routines to do a lot of the hard work for us. Another good example of this hybrid approach is the Filer, seen top-right, which needs to display arbitrary collections of files and directories as icons in a window.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>A contrived example</title>

<p>As might be expected, there will be a fair bit of new code needed before our application can redraw a window of its own, so we&rsquo;ll start by getting some groundwork in place. It might be useful if we could save the results of our calculations in a table for future reference, so let&rsquo;s create a results window to do just that.</p>

<p>Out first stop is in <cite>WinEd</cite>, to create a new window within our template file. We have called this &ldquo;Results&rdquo;, and it can be seen in <reference id="fig-redraw-window"/>.</p>

<image id="fig-redraw-window" file="redraw-window.png" title="Our new window template"/>

<p>For now, there will be few surprises in the new template. There are a couple of rows of icons along the top of the window, which will represent the rows and columns in our data table. Their widths have been sized to hold the longest text: the name of the shape in the first column, the text &ldquo;Sides&rdquo; in the second column, and the longest title &ndash; which is &ldquo;Internal Angles&rdquo; &ndash; in columns three to six.</p>

<p>With the icons spaced out neatly, the window&rsquo;s work area has been sized from 0 to 1260 OS&nbsp;units horizontally to fit. Vertically, the height of the icons is 52 OS&nbsp;units and so work area has been sized vertically from 0 to &minus;572 OS&nbsp;units to accommodate 10 lines of results and the title row.</p>

<p>The icons themselves are standard label icons, using the <icon>Comment</icon> icon from <cite>WinEd</cite>&rsquo;s <window>Icon picker</window>. We have changed the colours of the title row icons and adjusted the text alignment to get the desired appearance. The icons in the second row, which will eventually be used to display our data, have all been set to be indirected.</p>

<p>If any of this seems new or surprising, have a look back at <reference id="chap-templates"/> where we introduced window templates, and <reference id="chap-sprite-area"/> where we defined the work area of our main window.</p>

<p>If you know anything about window redraw already, you may be surprised that we haven&rsquo;t unticked the <icon>Auto redraw</icon> flag for the new window. This is because, for simplicity, we&rsquo;ll leave the Wimp to handle the redraw of our new window until we have it installed within the application code. It&rsquo;s always worth remembering that any redraw code related to a window can be taken out of use at any time for debugging by simply setting this flag in the window&rsquo;s definition.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>The results module</title>

<p>Moving to our application&rsquo;s source code, we will add a results module to look after the new window. Initially this will be very similar in concept to the ibar and win modules that we already have, so instead of going the the following code in detail we will refer back to where we previously introduced the concepts that we will need.</p>

<p>We will be adding a pair of new files &ndash; <file>c.results</file> and <file>h.results</file> &ndash; to create the new module, so our first step will be to update the <variable>OBJS</variable> list in the <file>Makefile</file> to include a reference to it.</p>

<code lang="makefile">OBJS = calc main menu ibar win results</code>

<p>The interface to the rest of the application will initially be very similar to the one used by the win module to look after the main window, and can be seen in <reference id="list-redraw-results-h"/> &ndash; take a look back at <reference id="list-windows-win-h"/> in <reference id="chap-windows"/> if you need a reminder of how we got here.</p>

<code lang="c" file="h.results" id="list-redraw-results-h" title="The header file to define the results module&rsquo;s interface"> /**
 * Example 31.1
 *
 * (c) Stephen Fryatt, 2026
 *
 * File: results.h
 */

#ifndef EXAMPLEAPP_RESULTS
#define EXAMPLEAPP_RESULTS

/* Results Initialisation. */

void results_initialise(void);

/* Open the Window. */

void results_open(void);

#endif</code>

<p>Our new <function>results_initialise()</function> function will need to be called from within <function>main_initialise()</function> in <file>c.main</file>, and we can add that call alongside the calls to the other initialisation functions as seen in <reference id="list-redraw-main-initialise"/>.</p>

<code lang="c" id="list-redraw-main-initialise" title="Initialising the results module">/* Initialise the program modules. */

calc_initialise();
ibar_initialise(main_application_sprite);
win_initialise(sprites);
results_initialise();</code>

<p>We can open the new results window with the currently unused <mouse>Adjust</mouse>-click on our iconbar icon, and this can be achieved by updating the <function>ibar_mouse_click()</function> fuction within <file>c.ibar</file> as seen in <reference id="list-redraw-ibar-click"/>.</p>

<code lang="c" id="list-redraw-ibar-click" title="Opening the results window from the iconbar icon">/* Mouse Click event handler */

static void ibar_mouse_click(wimp_pointer *pointer)
{
	switch (pointer-&gt;buttons) {
	case wimp_CLICK_SELECT:
		win_open();
		break;
	case wimp_CLICK_ADJUST:
		results_open();
		break;
	}
}</code>

<p>Initialising the new results window and its associated menu is done within the <function>results_initialise()</function> function, as seen in <reference id="list-redraw-results-init-1"/>.</p>

<code lang="c" id="list-redraw-results-init-1" title="Initialising the results window">/* Results Menu Entries. */

#define RESULTS_MENU_CLEAR 0

/* Global Variables. */

static wimp_w results_handle = NULL;
static wimp_menu *results_menu = NULL;

/* Function Prototypes. */

static void results_menu_selection(wimp_w window, wimp_menu *menu, wimp_selection *selection);

/* Results Window Initialisation. */

void results_initialise(void)
{
	os_error		*error;
	wimp_window		*window_definition;

	/* Load and create the window. */

	window_definition = windows_load_template(&quot;Results&quot;);
	if (window_definition == NULL) {
		error_msgs_report_error(&quot;BadResultsTempl&quot;);
		return;
	}

	results_handle = wimp_create_window(window_definition);
	free(results_handle);

	/* Window Menu. */

	results_menu = menu_create(&quot;ResultsMenu&quot;, 1);
	if (results_menu == NULL) {
		error_msgs_report_error(&quot;BadResultsMenu&quot;);
		return;
	}

	menu_entry(results_menu, RESULTS_MENU_CLEAR, &quot;ResultsMenu0&quot;, NULL);

	/* Register event handlers. */

	event_add_window_menu(results_handle, results_menu);
	event_add_window_menu_selection(results_handle, results_menu_selection);
}</code>

<p>We start by defining two global variables within the module: <variable>results_handle</variable> to hold the handle of the results window and <variable>results_menu</variable> to hold a pointer to the results window menu. The <name>RESULTS_MENU_CLEAR</name> constant is defined for the single entry that our new menu will have, and a prototype is set up for the <function>results_menu_selection()</function> function, to handle menu selections.</p>

<p>Within the function itself, we load the template for the window into a block of memory pointed to by <variable>*window_definition</variable>, then call <swi>Wimp_CreateWindow</swi> to create the window and free the block afterwards. This should all be familiar from <reference id="chap-templates"/>.</p>

<p>The menu is defined by calling <function>menu_create()</function> and <function>menu_entry()</function>, in the same way that we do for the main window and iconbar menus &ndash; see <reference id="chap-menus-intro"/>, <reference id="chap-menus-window"/> and <reference id="chap-mess-trans"/> for a reminder on how this works.</p>

<p>Finally, the menu is registered with the window and a handler is registered for receiving user selections &ndash; see <reference id="chap-menus-revisited"/> for details of SFLib&rsquo;s support for menus and event handlers.</p>

<p>The <function>results_menu_selection()</function> function for handling menu selections is defined in <reference id="list-redraw-results-menu-selection"/>. This is just a placeholder for now, and selection events will simply be ignored.</p>

<code lang="c" id="list-redraw-results-menu-selection" title="The placeholder for handling menu selections">/* Menu Selection event handler. */

static void results_menu_selection(wimp_w window, wimp_menu *menu, wimp_selection *selection)
{
	os_error *error;

	if (menu != results_menu)
		return;

	switch (selection-&gt;items[0]) {
	case RESULTS_MENU_CLEAR:
		break;
	}
}</code>

<p>The final piece of code that we need is the <function>results_open()</function> function, defined in <reference id="list-redraw-results-open"/>. This should be familiar from <reference id="chap-window-handling"/> and <reference id="chap-icons-radio"/>, when we created <reference id="sect-icons-radio-win-open">and then later modified</reference> the <function>win_open()</function> function.</p>

<code lang="c" id="list-redraw-results-open" title="Opening the results window on screen">/* Open the Window. */

void results_open(void)
{
	windows_open_centred_on_screen(results_handle);
}</code>

<p>The final thing that we need to do is to add the new message tokens to our messages file. Again, see <reference id="chap-mess-trans"/> for an explanation.</p>

<code lang="messtrans">ResultsMenu:Results
ResultsMenu0:Clear contents
BadResultsMenu:Failed to create Results Menu
BadResultsTempl:Failed to load Results template</code>

<p>With all of these changes in place, we should have an application with a results window: this can be opened, as seen in <reference id="fig-redraw-new-app"/>, using an <mouse>Adjust</mouse> click on the iconbar icon.</p>

<image id="fig-redraw-new-app" file="redraw-new-app.png" title="Our new results window in action"/>

<p>The updated code as it stands can be found in <reference id="dl-redraw-window"/>. There should be nothing surprising or unexpected here if you have followed the tutorial up to this point, but it would be worth making sure that you understand what has been added before we move on to make any changes!</p>

<download id="dl-redraw-window" file="RedrawWindow" title="The Results Window Structure" compatibility="none"/>
</section>


<section>
<title>Icon definitions</title>

<p>We have already noted that there are a range of approaches to drawing window content, from the completely Do-It-Yourself approach through to using the Wimp&rsquo;s icon plotting routines. If we&rsquo;re going to take the latter route, then we will need some standard icon data blocks to give to the Wimp; often, a good approach is to create these in the template for the window which is to be redrawn. This allows the icons to be designed graphically in a template editor, which is usually easier than creating them programatically.</p>

<p>As it stands in <reference id="dl-redraw-window"/>, our application is allowing the Wimp to create all of the icons in the Results window when the definition is passed to <swi>Wimp_CreateWindow</swi>, so that they appear when the window is opened. However, we can change this by altering the value of <variable>window_definition-&gt;icon_count</variable> in <function>results_initialise()</function>, between loading the template and passing the definition to <function>wimp_create_window()</function>.</p>

<p>If we wanted a completely empty window in which to draw our content, we could simply set the value to zero.</p>

<code lang="c">window_definition-&gt;icon_count = 0;</code>

<p>However, we are going to take an even more hybrid approach here: we will leave the Wimp to draw the icons in the heading line as normal, but will plot the lines of saved results data ourselves. This makes sense, as we don&rsquo;t know how many sets of results data there will be: it could be a couple of lines, or it could potentially be hundreds of even thousands (although, spoiler, to keep things simple, we won&rsquo;t be implementing limitless results storage in our example, so as to keep things simple).</p>

<p>We will start by defining some constants for the icons in our window template, in the usual way.</p>

<code lang="c">/* Results Window Icons. */

#define RESULTS_TITLE_ICONS 6

#define RESULTS_ICON_TITLE_SHAPE 0
#define RESULTS_ICON_TITLE_SIDES 1
#define RESULTS_ICON_TITLE_ANGLES 2
#define RESULTS_ICON_TITLE_LENGTH 3
#define RESULTS_ICON_TITLE_PERIMETER 4
#define RESULTS_ICON_TITLE_AREA 5
#define RESULTS_ICON_ROW_SHAPE 6
#define RESULTS_ICON_ROW_SIDES 7
#define RESULTS_ICON_ROW_ANGLES 8
#define RESULTS_ICON_ROW_LENGTH 9
#define RESULTS_ICON_ROW_PERIMETER 10
#define RESULTS_ICON_ROW_AREA 11</code>

<p>One thing to note here is that whilst the specific icon handles don&rsquo;t matter, it <em>is</em> important to ensure that we wish to let the Wimp create as normal <em>must</em> have lower handles than those which we intend to be used only as data blocks for the redraw process. We can see above (and by checking the templates file) that the title icons are numbered from 0 through to 5, and the icons which will form the data rows are numbered from 6 though to 11.</p>

<p>In addition to the icon handle definitions, we have also defined <name>RESULTS_TITLE_ICONS</name> to give the number of icons that form the title row in our design. This means that instead of setting <variable>icon_count</variable> to zero, we can set it to the number of icons that we wish to be created.</p>

<code lang="c">window_definition-&gt;icon_count = RESULTS_TITLE_ICONS;</code>

<p>We will also need to be able to access these icon definitions when we come to redraw our window. To this end, we will create a new global variable within <file>c.results</file> which can point to the icon definitions.</p>

<code lang="c">static wimp_icon *results_icons = NULL;</code>

<p>This can then be assigned within <function>results_initialise()</function>, once we have a pointer to the window definition returned from <function>windows_load_template()</function>.</p>

<code lang="c">results_icons = window_definition-&gt;icons;</code>

<p>The window definition returned by <function>windows_load_template()</function> is in a block of memory allocated by <function>malloc()</function>, so it won&rsquo; disappear when we exit the <function>results_initialise()</function>. However, we <em>do</em> need to remove the call to <function>free()</function> the memory after calling <function>wimp_create_window()</function>.</p>

<p>With the changes in place, the <function>results_initialise()</function> now looks as seen in <reference id="list-redraw-results-init-2"/>.</p>

<code lang="c" id="list-redraw-results-init-2" title="Initialising the results window">/* Results Window Initialisation. */

void results_initialise(void)
{
	os_error		*error;
	wimp_window		*window_definition;

	/* Load and create the window. */

	window_definition = windows_load_template(&quot;Results&quot;);
	if (window_definition == NULL) {
		error_msgs_report_error(&quot;BadResultsTempl&quot;);
		return;
	}

	window_definition-&gt;icon_count = RESULTS_TITLE_ICONS;

	results_icons = window_definition-&gt;icons;

	results_handle = wimp_create_window(window_definition);

	/* Window Menu. */

	results_menu = menu_create(&quot;ResultsMenu&quot;, 1);
	if (results_menu == NULL) {
		error_msgs_report_error(&quot;BadResultsMenu&quot;);
		return;
	}

	menu_entry(results_menu, RESULTS_MENU_CLEAR, &quot;ResultsMenu0&quot;, NULL);

	/* Register event handlers. */

	event_add_window_menu(results_handle, results_menu);
	event_add_window_menu_selection(results_handle, results_menu_selection);
}</code>

<p>When initialisation is complete, the icon data blocks will all remain in memory, and can be accessed from anywhere within <file>c.results</file> through the <variable>*results_icons</variable> pointer.</p>

<p>If we compile and run this code now, we should see that only the column headings icons are visible in the results window, as seen in <reference id="fig-redraw-icon-defs"/>. However, checking the templates file should confirm that all of the icons, including those intended for the data rows, are still defined there.</p>

<image id="fig-redraw-icon-defs" file="redraw-icon-defs.png" title="Hiding the icon definitions"/>

<p>To make it easier to follow the changes, <reference id="dl-redraw-icon-defs"/> contains the changes so far.</p>

<download id="dl-redraw-icon-defs" file="RedrawIconDefs" title="Removing the Unwanted Icons" compatibility="none"/>
</section>


<section>
<title>Redraw requirements</title>

<p>If you&rsquo;re familiar with writing software outside of the desktop, the way that window redraw works can seem somewhat counter-intuitive at first. When you want something to appear on the screen in a single-tasking application, you write or plot it to the screen; it then stays there until you plot over it with something else or clear the screen. On the desktop, things are not that simple.</p>

<p>The main difference is that our application won&rsquo;t be the only thing running on the system or writing to the screen. It must therefore only plot to the area within its windows, and &ndash; as we saw back in <reference id="chap-window-theory"/> &ndash; only part of a window&rsquo;s work area may be visible at any given time. There may also be other windows over ours, obscuring parts of them. Even worse, if another window or menu is dragged over one of ours, it will obliterate anything within our window that is in its path; when our window comes to the front again, its content will need to be reinstated.</p>

<p>As we might expect from the way that our application already interacts with other things like mouse clicks and keypresses, window redraw is an event driven process. If we don&rsquo;t set the <name>wimp_WINDOW_AUTO_REDRAW</name> flag in our window definition (or, in other words, clear <icon>Auto redraw</icon> in the template), then the Wimp will deliver us a <name>Redraw_Window_Request</name> event for the window whenever some or all of its contents need to be redrawn to the screen. As part of the event data, the Wimp will describe the area or areas which need to be plotted and we must comply <em>immediately</em>.</p>

<p>This leads to a second surprising consideration. If we wish to plot something to our window &ndash; perhaps the user has just saved a new result, which we need to add to our table &ndash; then we can&rsquo;t just go and plot it. Instead, we must tell the Wimp that we wish to update our window&rsquo;s contents, then wait for a <name>Redraw_Window_Request</name> event to arrive before the new content can be displayed. If the new content is in a part of the work area which isn&rsquo;t currently visible to the user, that <name>Redraw_Window_Request</name> event may not come for some time.</p>

<p>This leads us on to another potentially surprising consideration. An application which is redrawing its own data into a window will almost inevitably need to keep a full copy of that data internally, as it can be asked to redraw <em>any</em> part of the window at <em>any</em> time. This might be the application&rsquo;s raw data (for example, a word processor might just hold the document structure and render areas of the page from that when needed); at the other extreme, it may be easiest to render graphics to a sprite which can be plotted to screen on demand. Which route to take will depend a bit on the application, although I would usually lean towards keeping the data as &lsquo;raw&rsquo; as possible and plotting on demand as this is likely to minimise memory usage.</p>
</section>


<section>
<title>Adding a redraw loop</title>

<p>With the background laid, let&rsquo;s start to add some redraw code to our application. The first thing to do is to open the Redraw window template, go into the <window>Edit window</window> dialogue, and turn off the <icon>Auto redraw</icon> flag under <icon>Window behaviour</icon> (this is in <cite>WinEd</cite>, but other template editors will have a similar option). The window should start to display with a hatched background as seen in <reference id="fig-redraw-window-auto-off"/>, which is the template editor&rsquo;s way of showing us that it requires manual redrawing &ndash; most of the template editors, from <cite>FormEd</cite> onwards, use a similar approach.</p>

<image id="fig-redraw-window-auto-off" file="redraw-window-auto-off.png" title="Turning auto redraw off"/>

<p>With this change made, however, we <em>must</em> now update our application to correctly respond to <name>Redraw_Window_Request</name> events. Up to now, perhaps with the exception of <reference id="sect-key-input-hotkeys">not passing on keypresses correctly</reference>, it hasn&rsquo;t been too critical how we have reacted to events that the Wimp has sent us. However, when the Wimp sends us a <name>wimp_REDRAW_WINDOW_REQUEST</name> reason code through <swi>Wimp_Poll</swi>, we <em>must</em> respond correctly or our application will hang.</p>

<p>The Wimp supplies a <name>wimp_draw</name> structure with redraw events, which OSLib defines as follows.</p>

<code lang="c">struct wimp_draw
{
	wimp_w	w;
	os_box	box;
	int	xscroll;
	int	yscroll;
	os_box	clip;
};

typedef struct wimp_draw wimp_draw;</code>

<p>Inside, we get the usual <name>wimp_w</name> handle for the window which requires redrawing; at this point, none of the other fields have been populated. In fact, the use of <name>wimp_draw</name> here might be a little confusing: OSLib shares the struct around a number of related Wimp calls, because the Wimp API expects the same block pointer to be passed around a number of SWI calls.</p>

<p>On receipt of a <name>Redraw_Window_Request</name> event, our application must <em>immediately</em> call <swi>Wimp_RedrawWindow</swi> &ndash; in fact, the <cite>Programmer&rsquo;s Reference Manual</cite> states that calling this SWI must be &ldquo;the first Wimp operation after the <swi>Wimp_Poll</swi> which returned a <name>Window_Redraw_Request</name>&rdquo;. <swi>Wimp_RedrawWindow</swi> takes a pointer to the <name>wimp_draw</name> block that came with the event, and returns with the other fields in the block filled in.</p>

<code lang="c">extern osbool wimp_redraw_window(
	wimp_draw *redraw
);</code>

<p>In addition to completing the supplied <name>wimp_draw</name> block, <function>wimp_redraw_window()</function> also returns an <name>osbool</name> value which is <name>TRUE</name> if there is a redraw to be performed; in the unlikely event that it returns <name>FALSE</name>, then there is in fact nothing for our application to do.</p>

<p>Assuming that <function>wimp_redraw_window()</function> returned <name>TRUE</name>, the data in the <name>wimp_draw</name> block will contain enough information to enable our application to perform the operation that the Wimp is requesting. Once the operation is complete, our application should then call <swi>Wimp_GetRectangle</swi>.</p>

<code lang="c">extern osbool wimp_get_rectangle(
	wimp_draw *draw
);</code>

<p>As with <function>wimp_redraw_window()</function>, <function>wimp_get_rectangle()</function> takes a pointer to the same <name>wimp_draw</name> block and, if there are further redraw operations required from this event, it will update the contents of the block ready for the next one. It too returns an <name>osbool</name> value to indicate if the contents of the block needs to be attended to.</p>

<p>Armed with this knowledge, we can conclude that the simplest hander that we can supply for <name>Redraw_Window_Request</name> events is as follows.</p>

<code lang="c">static void results_redraw(wimp_draw *redraw)
{
	osbool more;

	more = wimp_redraw_window(redraw);

	while (more) {
		/* We could do some redrawing here... */

		more = wimp_get_rectangle(redraw);
	}
}</code>

<p>If registered as a handler for the <name>wimp_REDRAW_WINDOW_REQUEST</name> reason code, it will immediately call <function>wimp_redraw_window()</function> as required by the Wimp and record the returned <name>osbool</name> value in <variable>more</variable>. While <variable>more</variable> is <name>TRUE</name>, the handler will loop around, performing whatever redraw operations it needs to and then calling <function>wimp_get_rectangle()</function> to request the next set of data.</p>

<code lang="c">/* Register event handlers. */

event_add_window_redraw_event(results_handle, results_redraw);
event_add_window_menu(results_handle, results_menu);
event_add_window_menu_selection(results_handle, results_menu_selection);</code>

<p>If we add this <function>results_redraw()</function> to <file>c.results</file> and registr it as a handler for <name>Redraw_Window_Request</name> events by adding the code here to <function>results_initialise()</function>, our application will work correctly with the <icon>Auto redraw</icon> flag turned off in the Results window template. The window still looks exactly as it did in <reference id="fig-redraw-icon-defs"/> because we are not doing anything for any of the redraw operations requested by the Wimp, but the redraw loop is being executed each time the window is drawn or refreshed on screen.</p>

<p>For completeness, the changes so far can be found in  <reference id="dl-redraw-empty-loop"/>.</p>

<download id="dl-redraw-empty-loop" file="RedrawEmpty" title="A Minimal Redraw Loop" compatibility="none"/>
</section>


<section>
<title>Plotting some icons</title>

<p></p>


<code lang="c">osbool more;

more = wimp_redraw_window(redraw);

while (more) {
	/* We could do some redrawing here... */

	more = wimp_get_rectangle(redraw);
}</code>



<image id="fig-redraw-areas" file="redraw-areas.png" title="How the Wimp breaks down a redraw"/>




</section>
</chapter>
</manual>